Gerontology, Institute for; Records ua690.015
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Institute of Gerontology Records
1968-1995
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Institute of Gerontology (University at Albany)
ua690.015
11.6 cubic ft.
The records of the Institute of Gerontology include materials from the Institute on Aging, the Institute of Gerontology and the Ringel Institute of Gerontology, all of which served the same function within the State University of New York at Albany. Records include materials about program creation, correspondence, day files, grant applications, budgets, publications, research materials and professional development.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Web Archives
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, by the Ringel Institute for Gerontology in March 1995.
Administrative History
The Institute of Gerontology was the successor to the Institute on Aging, created in 1968 as part of the College of General Studies at the University at Albany, State University of New York. The purpose of the Institute, and all subsequent iterations, was to provide knowledge and research into the experience and care of elderly citizens. Specific issues such as nursing home care, criminal offenders and social interaction were the focus of instruction, communication and research through degree programs and certificates, seminars, conferences, newsletters, consortial committees and research studies. In 1972, the organization was renamed as the Institute of Gerontology, and became part of the University's School of Social Welfare. Within a few years, it received status as an established research unit. In 1982, it became the Ringel Institute for Gerontology, named for Rhoda and Stan Ringel, both of whom supported the mission of the institute. The name was changed again in 1997, back to the Institute of Gerontology, which it remains. It is currently comprised of two units, the Center for Research and the Center for Excellence in Aging Services.
Previous directors for the program include Father Anthony Rocha, Steven. I. Pflanczer, Susan R. Sherman and Sheldon S. Tobin. Primary researchers for the Institute include Evelyn S. Newman and Susan R. Sherman. Research topics continued to include elderly offenders, nursing home care, social interaction for seniors as well as the role of the University in advocating for this population, among others. Beyond research papers, the Institute hosted a number of conferences, seminars and training sessions.
Funding was initially provided through grants. After the first director, Father Anthony Rocha, failed to secure a necessary grant for a second consecutive year, he resigned from the Institute, which then was absorbed by the School of Social Welfare. From this point on, funding was received through a mix of grants and institutional funding.
Scope and Contents
Records contained in this collection include administrative files such as records documenting program creation, committee minutes and agendas, day files and correspondence from 1970-1995, financial records related to grand funding and budgets from 1968-1993, and publications including research projects, training seminars and conferences from 1970-1990. Records from the Ringel Institute of Gerontology follow those of the Institute of Gerontology within the same series. There are few remaining records from the Institute on Aging. Photographs and slides are included in the same boxes and folders as paper documents. Cassettes are housed separately in the Special Collections Cold Room.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into the following series:
Series are arranged chronologically.
Senior Citizens; Criminal Justice and Prisons; Education, Higher--New York (State); Older people--Social networks--New York (State); Elderly poor--New York (State); Frail elderly--Care--New York (State); Nursing home care--New York (State); Older offenders--United States; Financial Records; Correspondence; curricula; Research Notes; Audiocassettes; Videocassettes; Files by subject; Web Archives; UAlbany Centers & Institutes; Newman, Evelyn S.; Sherman, Susan--(Susan R.); State University of New York at Albany--Institute of Gerontology; State University of New York at Albany--School of Social Welfare; State University of New York at Albany
- General Correspondence, 1970-1995; Undated; 1; 2.1 cubic ft.
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains files relating to the creation of specific programs and certificates including the Nursing Home Ombudsman Program and Elderhostel Senior Seminar, day files, faculty searches, memos and correspondence of Evelyn Newman and Susan Sherman.
  - Partial Report on Activities, 1970-1971 (Box 1 (1-General Correspondence), Folder 1)
  - Day Files, 1971-1972 (Box 1 (1-General Correspondence), Folder 2)
  - Day Files, 1972-1973 (Box 1 (1-General Correspondence), Folder 3-4)
  - Day Files, 1973 March-August (Box 1 (1-General Correspondence), Folder 5-6)
  - Day Files, 1973-1974 (Box 1 (1-General Correspondence), Folder 7-8)
  - Day Files, 1974-1975 (Box 1 (1-General Correspondence), Folder 9)
  - Evelyn Newman Correspondence, 1974-1975 (Box 1 (1-General Correspondence), Folder 10)
  - Day Files, 1975 (Box 1 (1-General Correspondence), Folder 11)
  - Michelle Levy Certificate, Photo, 1975; Undated (Box 1 (1-General Correspondence), Folder 12)
  - Annual Report, 1975-1976 (Box 1 (1-General Correspondence), Folder 13)
  - Annual Reports, 1975-1976; 1978; 1980-1983; 1985 (Box 1 (1-General Correspondence), Folder 14)
  - Day Files, 1976; Undated (Box 1 (1-General Correspondence), Folder 15)
  - Local (Community) Advisory Committee Notebook, 1976-1980; Undated (Box 1 (1-General Correspondence), Folder 16)
  - General Correspondence, 1976-1983 (Box 1 (1-General Correspondence), Folder 18)
  - Day Files, 1977 (Box 1 (1-General Correspondence), Folder 18)
  - Nursing Home Ombudsman Program, 1977-1978 (Box 1 (1-General Correspondence), Folder 19-20)
  - Campus Advisory Board, 1977-1980; Undated (Box 1 (1-General Correspondence), Folder 21)
  - Elderhostel Senior Seminar, 1977-1981; Undated (Box 1 (1-General Correspondence), Folder 22)
  - Evelyn Newman Memos, 1977-1982 (Box 1 (1-General Correspondence), Folder 23)
  - NY State Nursing Home Ombudsman Final Report, 1978 (Box 1 (1-General Correspondence), Folder 24)
  - Day Files, 1978; Undated (Box 1 (1-General Correspondence), Folder 25)
  - Basic Adult Services: Model Curriculum, 1978-1981; Undated (Box 1 (1-General Correspondence), Folder 26)
  - Day Files, 1979 (Box 1 (1-General Correspondence), Folder 27)
  - Susan M. Sherman Correspondence, 1979-1980 (Box 1 (1-General Correspondence), Folder 28)
  - Undergraduate 2nd Field in Aging, 1979-1980; Undated (Box 1 (1-General Correspondence), Folder 29)
  - Adult Family Care Training, 1979-1980; Undated (Box 2 (1-General Correspondence), Folder 1-2)
  - Elderhostel Senior Seminar, 1979-1981; Undated (Box 2 (1-General Correspondence), Folder 3)
  - Community University Day, late 1970s (Cassette 1)
  - Certificate Program for Nursing Home Administrators, 1980; Undated (Box 2 (1-General Correspondence), Folder 4)
  - Day Files, 1980; Undated (Box 2 (1-General Correspondence), Folder 5)
  - Field of Study, 1980-1981; Undated (Box 2 (1-General Correspondence), Folder 6)
  - General Memos, 1980-1982; 1984-1989 (Box 2 (1-General Correspondence), Folder 7-8)
  - General Information, 1980-1985 (Box 2 (1-General Correspondence), Folder 9-10)
  - Day Files, 1981 (Box 3 (1-General Correspondence), Folder 1)
  - Faculty Search, 1981; Undated (Box 3 (1-General Correspondence), Folder 2)
  - Student Orientation, 1981-1982 (Box 3 (1-General Correspondence), Folder 3)
  - Agreement with the Ringels, 1981-1982; 1991 (Box 3 (1-General Correspondence), Folder 4)
  - Committees on Centers and Institutes, 1981-1982; Undated (Box 3 (1-General Correspondence), Folder 5)
  - Development of Program, 1981-1982; Undated (Box 3 (1-General Correspondence), Folder 6-7)
  - Five-Year Plan, 1981-1982; 1988-1989; Undated (Box 3 (1-General Correspondence), Folder 8)
  - Day Files, 1982 (Box 3 (1-General Correspondence), Folder 9)
  - Minor in Maturity and Aging, 1982-1983 (Box 3 (1-General Correspondence), Folder 10)
  - Annual Lecture, 1983; 1986-1988; 1991-1993; 1995 (Box 3 (1-General Correspondence), Folder 11)
  - Director's Report, 1987-1989; 1992 (Box 3 (1-General Correspondence), Folder 12)
  - Search for PSTP Associate Director, 1988 (Box 3 (1-General Correspondence), Folder 13)
  - Evaluation of Library Resources, 1989; Undated (Box 3 (1-General Correspondence), Folder 14)
  - Institute Review, 1989; Undated (Box 3 (1-General Correspondence), Folder 15)
  - Search for Center for Women in Government Director, 1990; Undated (Box 3 (1-General Correspondence), Folder 16)
  - General Memos, 1990-1994 (Box 3 (1-General Correspondence), Folder 17)
  - Consortium on Aging, 1991 (Box 3 (1-General Correspondence), Folder 18)
  - Memo re: Registration, 1991 (Box 3 (1-General Correspondence), Folder 19)
  - Research Associate, 1991 (Box 3 (1-General Correspondence), Folder 20)
  - Review and Site Visit, 1991 (Box 3 (1-General Correspondence), Folder 21)
  - Steering Committee, 1991 (Box 3 (1-General Correspondence), Folder 22)
  - Consortium on Aging, 1991-1995 (Box 4 (1-General Correspondence), Folder 1)
- Financial Files, 1968-1993; Undated; 2; 1.0 cu. ft.
  This series contains financial records that include funding proposals, grant applications and budgets.
  - Draft Proposal for Funding the Program on Aging of the State University of New York at Albany, 1968 (Box 1 (2-Financial Files), Folder 1)
  - Institute of Gerontology Funding, 1971; 1979-1980; Undated (Box 1 (2-Financial Files), Folder 2)
  - Regional Multidisciplinary Gerontology Center, Title IV-C Grant, 1976-1980; Undated (Box 1 (2-Financial Files), Folder 3-4)
  - Title IV-A Grant, Year 2, Supporting Documents, 1977-1980 (Box 1 (2-Financial Files), Folder 5)
  - Title IV-C Grant, Quarterly and Final Reports, 1977-1980; Undated (Box 1 (2-Financial Files), Folder 6)
  - Title IV-C Grant Correspondence, 1978-1979 (Box 1 (2-Financial Files), Folder 7)
  - US Administration on Aging, Title IV-A Grant, Final Report and Other Materials, 1978-1980; Undated (Box 1 (2-Financial Files), Folder 8)
  - Title IV-A Grant Proposal Year 2 Correspondence, 1979; Undated (Box 1 (2-Financial Files), Folder 9)
  - Title IV-A Grant Proposal, Year 2, 1979; Undated (Box 2 (2-Financial Files), Folder 1-2)
  - Advocacy Assistance Training Grant, 1979-1980; Undated (Box 2 (2-Financial Files), Folder 3)
  - Research Foundation of SUNY, Preapplication Grant. Not Funded, 1982 (Box 2 (2-Financial Files), Folder 4)
  - Budget, 1982-1989; Undated (Box 2 (2-Financial Files), Folder 5)
  - NIA Program Project Grant, 1984; Undated (Box 2 (2-Financial Files), Folder 6-8)
  - Budget, 1985-1991; Undated (Box 3 (2-Financial Files), Folder 1)
  - IFR Budget, 1991; 1993 (Box 3 (2-Financial Files), Folder 2)
- Publicity, Research and Professional Development, 1970-1990; Undated; 3; 1.91 cu. ft.
  This series contains newsletters and brochures, materials developed for conferences and seminars and faculty research publications.
  - County Aging Profile Series Demographics and Housing Patterns - 1930-1970 (Box 1 (3-Publicity, Research and Professional D), Folder 1)
  - “The Poor of the Capital District” A Research Memo, 1970 (Box 1 (3-Publicity, Research and Professional D), Folder 2)
  - “Public Policy and the Elderly in NY State” Notebook, 1971-1975; 1980-1982 (Box 1 (3-Publicity, Research and Professional D), Folder 3)
  - Publicity Notebook, 1971-1975; 1980-1982 (Box 1 (3-Publicity, Research and Professional D), Folder 4)
  - “Planning for Social Welfare: Coordinating Area Number 3” A Regional Factbook – IG Report, 1972 (Box 1 (3-Publicity, Research and Professional D), Folder 5)
  - “Planning for Social Welfare: The People of Albany, Selected Census Data for Albany, NY”, 1973 (Box 1 (3-Publicity, Research and Professional D), Folder 6)
  - Proceedings of the Regional Conference on Aging, 1973 (Box 1 (3-Publicity, Research and Professional D), Folder 7)
  - Regional Conference on Aging, 1973 (Box 1 (3-Publicity, Research and Professional D), Folder 8)
  - Research Memo: “Poverty in Albany County”, 1973 (Box 1 (3-Publicity, Research and Professional D), Folder 9)
  - Regional Conference on Aging - Sonoma Nixon Correspondence, 1973; Undated (Box 1 (3-Publicity, Research and Professional D), Folder 10)
  - Slides of Conference Photos and Presentations, 1973; 1975; Undated (Box 1 (3-Publicity, Research and Professional D), Folder 11)
  - Conference Brochures, 1973-1976; 1979-1980; Undated (Box 1 (3-Publicity, Research and Professional D), Folder 12)
  - “The Albany Senior Service Center Nutritional Program: Its Characteristics, Its Participants”, 1975 (Box 1 (3-Publicity, Research and Professional D), Folder 13)
  - “Crimes Against the Elderly in Public Housing: Policy Alternatives”, 1975 (Box 1 (3-Publicity, Research and Professional D), Folder 14)
  - Gerontology Colloquium Slide Presentation and Discussion by Dr. Jane Ives. “Services to the Elderly in Denmark.” (Flyer), 1976 (Box 1 (3-Publicity, Research and Professional D), Folder 15)
  - “The Meaning of Cherished Personal Possessions for the Elderly”, 1976 (Box 1 (3-Publicity, Research and Professional D), Folder 16)
  - “Modes of Retirement Housing for the Elderly,” Brief Summary of the Final Report, 1976 (Box 1 (3-Publicity, Research and Professional D), Folder 17)
  - “Options in Intermediate Sheltered Housing for the Elderly”, 1976 (Box 1 (3-Publicity, Research and Professional D), Folder 18-19)
  - “The Role of State University Systems in Opportunities for Senior Citizens”, 1976 (Box 1 (3-Publicity, Research and Professional D), Folder 20)
  - Questionnaire for Retirement Planning Sent to Faculty and Non-teaching Professionals of SUNY, 1976; 1978 (Box 1 (3-Publicity, Research and Professional D), Folder 21)
  - Publicity Notebook, 1976-1979; Undated (Box 1 (3-Publicity, Research and Professional D), Folder 22)
  - “Toward Services for the Elderly: Regional Data of a Roman Catholic Diocese”, 1977 (Box 1 (3-Publicity, Research and Professional D), Folder 23)
  - Miscellaneous, 1977; 1980-1985 (Box 1 (3-Publicity, Research and Professional D), Folder 24)
  - “Reading, Language and Communication”, 1977-1978 (Box 1 (3-Publicity, Research and Professional D), Folder 25)
  - Newsletters, 1977-1981 (Box 1 (3-Publicity, Research and Professional D), Folder 26)
  - “Differences in Attitudes Toward Retirement Among Male and Female Faculty and Other University Professionals”, 1978 (Box 1 (3-Publicity, Research and Professional D), Folder 27)
  - “Foster-family Care for the Elderly: Surrogate Family or Mini-Institution?”, 1978 (Box 1 (3-Publicity, Research and Professional D), Folder 28)
  - “The Role of the Case Worker in Adult Foster Care”, 1978 (Box 1 (3-Publicity, Research and Professional D), Folder 29)
  - Survey of Opportunities in the Field of Gerontology in Forty-three Educational Institutions in N.Y.S.: Summary of Findings, 1978 (Box 1 (3-Publicity, Research and Professional D), Folder 30)
  - Advocacy Assistance for Older Adults Conference, 1978; Undated (Box 1 (3-Publicity, Research and Professional D), Folder 31)
  - “Day Treatment for the Elderly: An Overview”, 1979 (Box 1 (3-Publicity, Research and Professional D), Folder 32)
  - Directory of Services: A Guide for Adult Family Care Providers Participating in the 1979 Summer Training Session (Box 1 (3-Publicity, Research and Professional D), Folder 33)
  - Elderly Offender Conference, 1979 (Cassette 2-7)
  - “Group Services for the Elderly in Albany County: A Directory”, 1979 (Box 1 (3-Publicity, Research and Professional D), Folder 34)
  - “Social Participation in Adult Homes: Deinstitutionalized Mental Patients and the Frail Elderly”, 1979 (Box 1 (3-Publicity, Research and Professional D), Folder 35)
  - “Training Citizen Ombudsmen” (Prepared for presentation at Educational Innovations Exchange, Annual Program Meeting), 1979 (Box 1 (3-Publicity, Research and Professional D), Folder 36)
  - A Workshop for Family Care Takers: Problem Solving Part I, 1979; 1 U-matic tape.; 2 VHS tapes. Both duplicates of U-matic tape. (Video-tape 1-3)
  - A Workshop for Family Care Takers: Problem Solving Part II, 1979; 1 U-matic tape.; 2 VHS tapes. Both duplicates of U-matic tape. (Video-tape 4-6)
  - A Workshop for Family Care Takers: Problem Solving Part III, 1979; 1 U-matic tape.; 2 VHS tapes. Both duplicates of U-matic tape. (Video-tape 7-9)
  - “Understanding the Psycho-Social Needs of the Elderly in Family Care Residents” Training, 1979; Undated (Box 1 (3-Publicity, Research and Professional D), Folder 37)
  - Homebound Elderly, Includes Photo, 1979-1980; Undated (Box 1 (3-Publicity, Research and Professional D), Folder 38)
  - Conference Proceedings: New York State Perspectives on Aging, 1980 (Box 2 (3-Publicity, Research and Professional D), Folder 1)
  - “The Development of a Curriculum in Gerontology for the Public Health Sector”, 1980 (Box 2 (3-Publicity, Research and Professional D), Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous Conferences and Seminars, 1980-1982; Undated (Box 2 (3-Publicity, Research and Professional D), Folder 3)
  - Al Abrams Dinner, 1981 (Box 2 (3-Publicity, Research and Professional D), Folder 4)
  - Newsletters, 1981 (Box 2 (3-Publicity, Research and Professional D), Folder 5)
  - Mental Health and the Elderly Lecture Series, 1981; Undated (Box 2 (3-Publicity, Research and Professional D), Folder 6)
  - Rockefeller Research Committees, 1981; Undated (Box 2 (3-Publicity, Research and Professional D), Folder 7)
  - “Community Integration of Mentally Ill Adults in (Foster) Family Care”, 1981-1982 (Box 2 (3-Publicity, Research and Professional D), Folder 8)
  - Elderly Offender Conference, 1982 (Cassette 8-11)
  - Elderly Offender Conference, 1982 (Box 2 (3-Publicity, Research and Professional D), Folder 9)
  - Elderly Offender Conference Planning Documents, 1982 (Box 2 (3-Publicity, Research and Professional D), Folder 10-11)
  - Survey of Graduate Degree Recipients, 1982-1985 (Box 2 (3-Publicity, Research and Professional D), Folder 12)
  - Research Proposal, 1985-1987 (Box 2 (3-Publicity, Research and Professional D), Folder 13)
  - Eugene S. Callender will Present the Fourth Annual Ringel Lecture on “Targeting the Needs of the Elderly” (Flyer), 1986 (Box 2 (3-Publicity, Research and Professional D), Folder 14)
  - Self-Study Team, 1989; Undated (Box 3 (3-Publicity, Research and Professional D), Folder 1-2)
  - “Peterson’s Annual Survey of Graduate Institutions”, 1990 (Box 3 (3-Publicity, Research and Professional D), Folder 3)
- Web Archives, 2010 May 28-2016 September 18; 4; 278 captures
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Web crawling is managed through the Internet Archive's Archive-It service. This page includes links to both the university's collection and the Internet Archive's public collection.
  Surface-level crawling of www.albany.edu is performed daily which should includes most top-level webpages. Separate targeted crawls of every albany.edu subdomain are performed monthly to attempt to gather all content. This includes: www.albany.edu, www.rna.albany.edu, www.ctg.albany.edu, www.ualbanysports.com, www.albany.edu/rockefeller, www.albany.edu/cela, www.albany.edu/asrc, m.albany.edu, library.albany.edu, events.albany.edu, cstar.cestm.albany.edu, csda.albany.edu, and alumni.albany.edu
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  Web Archives
  - http://www.albany.edu/outreach/Institute_of_Gerontology.php - University Archives collection, 2013 May 8-2016 September 18 (Web-archive 1)
  - WARC file for http://www.albany.edu/outreach/Institute_of_Gerontology.php, (please see https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Web_ARChive for more details), 2013 May 8-2016 September 18 (Warc 1)
    Conditions Governing Access
    WARC files are very large and difficult to work with. Your request may take time to process, and we may be unable to deliver your request remotely. Please consult an archivist if you are interested in researching with web archives.
  - http://www.albany.edu/outreach/Institute_of_Gerontology.php - Internet Archive collection, 2010 May 28-2016 September 18 (Web-archive 2)